A Guide to the Papers of Homer G. Richey, [1946-1960]-1988
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Homer G. Richey [1946-1960]-1988
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12709
This collection consists of ca. 175 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the library in 1989 January 20 by Dr. Richey.
Biographical/Historical Information
Homer G. Richey born ca. 1908 and is a native of Albemarle County, Virginia. He received his BA. and MA. from the Goettingen University in Germany and his Ph.D. from the University of Virginia? He studied and travelled widely. He served in the United States Air Force, taught German in the Army School of Military Government in Charlottesville, Virginia and was an instructor in the Disarmament School in London. He served as an Assistant Professor of Foreign Affairs at the University of Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 175 items (1 Hollinger Box, ca. 0.3 linear shelf feet) and dates from approximately 1946 to 1960, and 1988. This collection is comprised of correspondence regarding Homer G. Richey's dismissal as a member of the faculty of the Woodrow Wilson School of International Studies of the University of Virginia; in addition, it includes the minutes of the meetings of the Board of Visitors, press releases and transcripts of his radio broadcasts.
Organization
The collection is organized in 3 groups: 1. Introduction 2. Dr. Richey's fight with Colgate Darden, John Frederic Gange etc. and 3. Untitled
Contents List
- "By the Way of Introduction" [1988]--Typescripts
- "My fight with Darden, Gange etc." --Typescripts, Articles, Notes and Correspondence
- To Walter Lippman ( Herald-Tribune) from John Gange re "The Formusa Crusade" (Washington Post) 1960 Jan 11 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Governor William H. Hastie from Gange re nomination as judge of the 3rd Circuit Court of appeals 1949 Oct 28 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Editor Daily Progress from Richey 1951 Aug 29 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Richey from Sara Mc. Q. Taylor re letter of appreciation [?] Nov 30 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Dean Acheson from Gange re letter in appreciation 1950 Jan 17 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Charles Barham, Jr., WCHV radio from Governor John S. Battle re letter in appreciation 1950 Dec 22 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Wm. H. Ruffin, President of Irwin Mills from Battle re giving assistance to Richey's ideas 1950 Dec 22 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Hardy C. Dillard, University of Virginia Law from Col. Frank F. Miter re letter in appreciation 1946 Feb 27 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Dillard from Lt. Col. Stanley J. Leyland re letter of recommendation 1946 Mar 1 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Dillard from Col. Frank Kowalski re recommendation 1946 Mar 6 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To E. I. Carruthers from Pres. Newcomb re Richey's appointment in W. W. School of International Studies 1946 Jul 2 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Darden from Gange memo re promotions 1950 May 10 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Gov. Battle from Richey memo - 'Aide Memoire' 1951 Feb 2 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Sen. Harry F. Byrd from Richey re 'Aide Memoire' 1951 Feb 2 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Hon. William M. Tuck, Attorney from Richey re 'Aide Memoire' 1951 Feb 2 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Gov. Battle from Richey re 'Aide Memoire' 1951 Feb 2 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Richey from John [Battle] re broadcast scripts [-] Nov 29 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Gov. Battle from Richey re radio broadcast 1951 Feb 10 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Pres. Colgate Darden from Gange re Richey's accusations 1951 Feb 8 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Richey from Sen. Harry F. Byrd reply to letter 1951 Feb 2 1951 Feb 7 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Darden from Richey re future development of W. W. school 1951 Feb 10 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Richey from Darden re Richey's charges 1951 Feb 12 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Richey from Wm. M. Tuck reply to letter 1951 Feb 2 1951 Feb 5 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Hon. W. Tuck from Richey reply to letter 1951 Feb 5 1951 Feb 6 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Darden from Richey re request of copy of report prepared by Gange 1951 Feb 24 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Richey from Darden reply to letter 1951 May 24 1951 Feb 26 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Darden from Richey re his views and actions 1951 Feb 28 (Folder 2 of 7)
- To Richey from Joseph P. Kamp, ( Headlines) re Gange's literature 1951 Mar 7 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Representative Richard Vail from Paul F. Kinnucan, student re Gange's teachings 1951 Mar 15 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Richey from Dean Ivey F. Lewis re looking into the situation 1951 Apr 14 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Dean Lewis from Richey reply to letter 1951 Apr 14 1951 Apr 18 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Barron Foster Black, Rector, Board of Visitors from Richey memo - Petition of Richey 1951 Apr 25 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To I. F. Lewis from Richey letter enclosing copy of petition 1951 Apr 25 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Darden from Richey letter enclosing copy of petition 1951 Apr 25 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Barron Black from Richey re presenting petition only to the Board 1951 Apr 26 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Richey from Darden re receipt of petition 1951 Apr 27 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Richey from Barron Black re Richey's personal presentation before the Board 1951 May 7 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To members of Board of Visitors absent on May 11 from Richey memo - Facts relating to the appointment of Richey 1951 May 14 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Barron Black from John M. Gallagher, Jr, ex-student letter appreciating Richey's teachings 1951 May 22 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Richey from J. M. Gallagher enclosing copy of letter sent to Black n.d. (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Richey from Vincent Shea, Secretary - Board of Visitors re copy of "Report of the Committee on Foreign Affairs" dt. 1951 May 8 1951 May 14 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Rector, Board of Visitors from Richey memo - Answer to the report 1951 May 28 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Richey from Benj W. Mears re reply to letter May 28 1951 May 29 (Folder 3 of 7)
- To Barron Black from Robert A. Shaid ex-student letter appreciating Richey's teachings 1951 Jun 1 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Rector, Board of Visitors from Grant R. Sherk ex-student letter appreciating Richey's teachings 1951 Jun 4 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To whom it may concern from James E. Ammons ex-student letter appreciating Richey's teachings 1951 Jun 5 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Barron Black from Richey letter with his forwarding address 1951 Jun 16 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Richey from Black re supplying notes to Gange, Fernbach & Micaud 1951 Jun 21 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Black from Richey re providing copies to Gange, Fernbach & Micaud 1951 Jun 24 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Black from Richey re inaccuracies in the minutes 1951 Jun 25 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Rector and Board of Visitors from Richey memo - Suggested additions & corrections to the minutes of the Board of Visitors meeting 1951 Jun 25 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Richey from Rector, Board of Visitors letter of thanks 1951 Jun 26 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Richey from [Thomas Gay?] re reply to letter June 25 1951 Jun 27 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Thomas Gay from Richey re inaccuracies in the minutes 1951 Jun 29 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Black from Richey re provision of copies of letters previously withheld 1951 Jul 1 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Vincent Shea, Secretary from Richey re enclosing copies of related documents 1951 Jul 2 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To E. I. Carruthers from J. L. Newcomb re Richey's appointment and remuneration 1946 Jul 2 (Folder 4 of 7)
- To Vincent Shea from Richey re comments on minutes 1951 Jul 6 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Rector, Board of Visitors from Richey memo - Comments on minutes of Board of Visitors meeting, Charlottesville, 1951 June 7 1951 Jul 6 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Vincent Shea from Gange re receipt of copy of minutes 1951 Jul 7 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Rector, Board of Visitors from Richey memo - Rebuttal of Prof Gange's testimony before the Board of Visitors given on July 12, 1951 1951 Aug 19 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Barron Black from Richey re Richey's rebuttal and being approached by Washington Times Herald1951 Aug 22 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Black from Richey re reply to letter Aug 23 1951 1951 Aug 26 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Edward Anderson from Richey re enclosing a copy of rebuttal of Gange's testimony 1951 Aug 26 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Louis Budenz, Fordham University from Richey re information on Gange 1951 Aug 27 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Mary Stalcup Markward from Richey re information on Gange 1951 Aug 27 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Richey from Black re reply to letter Aug 26, 1951 1951 Aug 27 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Black from Richey re provision of radio broadcasts scripts 1951 Aug 28 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Richey from Black re Board's denial of Richey's petition 1951 Sep 15 (Folder 5 of 7)
- From Richey - Press Release 1951 Sep 16 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Colgate Darden from Richey re reaction to the resolution 1951 Sep 17 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Black from [Richey] re reaction & comments on the resolution 1951 Sep 22 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Richey from Black re reply to letter Sep 22, 1951 1951 Sep 24 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Black from Richey re reply to letter Sep 24, 1951 1951 Oct 10 (Folder 5 of 7)
- To Richey from Vincent Shea re transcripts of minutes of meeting Sep 13, 1951 1951 Oct 15 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Black from Richey re comments on the Board's statement on the case 1952 Jan 9 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Black from Richey re reply to letter Jan 10 and additional comments 1952 Jan 12 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Richey from Black re reply to letter Jan 12 1952 Jan 16 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Richey from Black re reply to letter Oct 10. 1951 1951 Oct 13 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Richey from Black re reply to letter Sep 18, 1951 1951 Sep 19 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Richey from Darden re relieving Richey of his assignment as a member of staff of W. W. School 1951 Sep 17 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Darden from Dean - 1. Dept. of Graduate Studies 2. Dept. of Engineering 3. College of Arts and Sciences 4. of Women 5. Dept. of Medicine 6. Dept. of Law 7. Dept. of Education & 8. of Summer Session re Richey's removal 1951 Sep 15 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Richey from James E. [?] re trying to help Richey 1951 Jun 5 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Richey from Darden re cancellation of Richey's request of being Acting Associate Professor 1950 Oct 20 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Darden from Gange re Richey's position in the school 1950 Sep 26 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Darden from Richey re refusal of promotion to Acting Associate Professor 1950 Sep 26 (Folder 6 of 7)
- To Charles Barham, Jr. WCHV radio from Richey re termination of Richey's broadcasts 1951 Sep 25 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Ivey Lewis from Richey re translation of Jefferson's notes on Virginia 1951 Oct 2 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Richey from Black re reply to his letter enclosing rebuttal of Gange's testimony 1951 Aug 23 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To John M. Gallagher, Jr., Vice-Pres. Atlas Butchers Incorporated from Black re reply to his letter of interest in the school 1951 May 25 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Richey from Black re reply to Richey's letter May 23, 1951 1951 May 25 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Black from Richey re copies of letter in support of his petition 1951 May 23 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Albert G. A. Balz, Dept. of Philosophy from Richey re appointment as an Associate Professor 1946 Apr 23 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Mrs. James L. Spencer (Ann) from Richey re appointment as an Associate Professor 1951 May 15 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To E. I. Carruthers from Newcomb re Richey's appointment as an Assistant Professor and his remuneration 1946 Jul 2 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Mary S. Markward from Richey re information on Gange 1951 Aug 27 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To E. I. Carruthers from Newcomb re appointment of Richey as an Assistant Professor 1946 Jul 2 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Darden from Richey re reply to letter Feb 26 and views on Gange's report 1951 Feb 28 (Folder 7 of 7)
- Letters from Students - (Folder 7 of 7)
- From George Weber on Richey's teachings 1948 Apr 12 (Folder 7 of 7)
- From Hugh Ross on Richey's teachings 1948 Apr 13 (Folder 7 of 7)
- From Wirt A. Laun, Jr. on Richey's teachings 1948 Apr 12 (Folder 7 of 7)
- From Robert B. Shea on Richey's teachings 1948 May 1 (Folder 7 of 7)
- From Howard B. Helm on Richey's teachings 1948 Apr 20 (Folder 7 of 7)
- From Donald Rumsey on Richey's teachings 1948 May 10 (Folder 7 of 7)
- From Ronald J. Richard on Richey's teachings 1948 Apr 28 (Folder 7 of 7)
- From Bates Gilliam on Richey's teachings 1948 Apr 18 (Folder 7 of 7)
- From Cummins E. Speakman, Jr. on Richey's teachings 1948 Apr 13 (Folder 7 of 7)
- From J. T. S. Lyle, Jr. on Richey's teachings 1951 May 28 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Richey from McQ. Taylor on Richey's teachings 1947 Nov 30 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Richey from Ed. Carris on Richey's teachings 1949 Jul 13 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Gooch from Richey memo - Justification for Promotion of Richey to Associate Professor 1948 Feb 11 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Editor, Daily Progress from Richey memo - Your right to say it 1955 Apr 1 (Folder 7 of 7)
- To Dillard, Prof. of Law from Col. Frank F. Miter re Richey's teachings 1946 Feb 27
- To Col. Dillard from Lt. Col. Stanley J. Leland, Medical Corps on Richey's teachings 1946 Mar 1
- To Dillard from Col. Frank Kowalski, Infantry re Richey's teachings 1946 Mar 6
- To Darden from Richey re criticisms of his abilities as a teacher 1948 Apr 15
- To Richey from Darden re reply to letter dated 15th 1948 Apr 17
- To Richey from Darden re reply to letter dated 18th 1948 May 24
- To Darden from Richey re letters from students 1948 May 18
- From George Weber 1948 Apr 12
  see previous letter, 'My fight...' 7 of 7
- From Hugh Ross 1948 Apr 13
- From Wirt A. Laun, Jr. Capt. USAF 1948 Apr 12
- From Cummins E. Speakman, Jr. 1948 Apr 13
- From Ronald J. Richard 1948 Apr 28
- From Bates Mccluer Gilliam 1948 Apr 18
- From Lyle, Jr. 1948 May 28
- From Donald Rumsey 1948 May 10
- From Howard B. Helm 1948 Apr 20
- From Robert Shea 1948 May 1
- To Darden from Donald Rumsey 1948 May 10
- To Richey from G. B. Masters, Program Chairman Kiwanis Club of Winchester re giving a talk on 'International Scene Today' 1949 Jul 2
- To Richey from Laun re letter of appreciation 1948 Apr 12
- From George Weber 1948 Apr 12
- To Richey from RBS letter of appreciation 1948 May 1
- To Richey from Donald Rumsey re duplicates of his letters to Darden and University of Virginia n.d.
- From Lyle 1948 May 28
- To Richey from Ed Carris 1949 Jul 13